Hello and welcome back to week three of Python applied core and applied concepts.
So in this week we will be mostly covering module three which is about you know reasoning
with assignment conditional and loops.
So before we proceed with today's lecture so let me briefly talk about what we discussed
in the last week.
So this was roughly what we were discussing in the last week we talked about Python expression
hierarchy.
We learned how to build simple expressions, whether it be arithmetic expression logical
expression or other kind of you know lambda expressions using operators.
We went to the assignment expression which is distinctive from assignment statement.
And we discussed the distinction between these two with carefully chosen example and then
we moved on to lambda expression and discussed about lambda expression in you know some detail.
We tried to emphasize that lambda expression are nameless functions and at multiple places
they can be you know of use or they can be preferred over a simple function for which
we have names.
So lambda expressions are nameless functions.
So if you feel like you don't need to give a name to a particular function and you
still want to use that function maybe you know the best choice is lambda expression.
So we discussed about this so please go through those lecture if you can't recall you
know some of this concept.
So yeah so with this let me go to today's topic which is mostly about assignment statement.
So this week we will be mostly talking about assignment statement then you know conditionals
in Python programming language and going ahead we will also see how to write loops and
where can loops help us you know do some computation which is otherwise not possible using
you know primitive concept like assignment and only conditionals.
So now let me go directly to the non Jupyter notebook so again so we are here and what
you can see is this model 3 which will be reasoning about assignment conditional and loops.
So let's begin with the simplest one so although we have discussed in some you know detail
this assignment statement when we were discussing about assignment expression but let us
discuss today the semantics a little bit you know clearly so let's do a deep dive into this
assignment statement with some very simple example which many of you might have seen earlier.
So the idea today is to understand the semantics of assignment properly okay so and it can be
understood only if we know focus on some simple very simple example very very you know simplest
kind of example that can let us focus on the semantics rather than the you know complex syntax of
the whole programming language. So assignments as I mentioned in the very you know first video
are maybe the you know only way by which you can change the state of abstract machine okay and
remember we are talking about a statement and normally statements are mean to change the state
of abstract machine for your language okay so when we execute a statement one after another what
we are actually doing is we are trying to change the state of machine in particular no way
so that we achieve the kind of computation that we wanted to achieve okay so we always have
intention in mind and then we want to translate that intention into a sequence of instructions
and what finally those sequence of instruction does is changes the state of machine in a careful way
so that what you get as a final you know state is you know what you intended to get as a computation
of a let's say desired function or something like that okay so let me you know begin with very
simple example so just you know quickly recap so what is the I think you can see my Jupiter notebook now
so let me highlight the syntax of this assignment expression okay so before we go about this
semantics let's talk about the syntax about the most you know simple syntax we have seen some
syntactic sugar also in the last class where you can actually assign multiple you know variables
simultaneously but let's talk about the simplest one and well if you know ideas clear about the
simplest one then you will not do any mistake with you know more let's say sophisticated way in
which you can use maybe assignment to assign multiple things or you know change assignment or
something you know that we discuss in the last class so the simplest one is you have one variable
let's say on the left hand side and on the right hand side what you have is an expression okay so
this is the syntax of let's say assignment expression and now we want to know what is the effect of
let's say executing this instruction on the state of Michigan right so that's what we call you know
semantics of the meaning of this meaning of executing this instruction okay so you see I mean
there are two things on the left hand side you have a variable you know with somehow you know
points to something in memory which try to abstract out you know these memory you know registers
or main memory and on this right hand side you have an expression okay we we have already seen
right what an expression is in the last class you can know build simple expression and then
complicated expression using operators no form those simple expressions so on the right hand side
you can put any expression okay so this expression on the right hand side now always evaluates to
some value okay so what we call here is you values from value and or an object okay so why we are
calling object because no right hand side may not always no evaluate to let's say some you know
data types you know primitive data type that you know like integers you know or string or
these kind of things so right hand side may also evaluate to object which represent functions let's
say right and in the last lecture we saw that we also you know you know defined remaining
full function you using lambda expression and then assign those expressions to the variable on
the left so so remember I mean this distinction these expressions need not always be the value the
kind of value that comes to your mind you know by default like natural numbers string no I mean
they can be no more complicated nothing like no function objects which are nothing but functions
okay so you can also consider them as no value but then you know you have to be clear that when we
say value we don't say no value in this restrictive sense of you know the data types only okay so
great so our expression no on the right hand side evaluate to some value and then in the second
step what happens is we bind now this value to the variable name that we have given on the left
inside okay so this is you know two step you know operational semantics the first step is you
evaluate the expression okay and remember that evaluating the expression may not always change
the state of the machine okay so so this is what we also discussed right in the last class that
we normally don't want you know expressions or evaluation of expressions to change the state
of our abstract machine but then there are you know certain you know expressions like you know
expression which will actually change the state of machine so not true always but you know
most of the time we want it to be true okay so then I mean how this instruction or this you know
statement in programming language is changing the state of the machine so even though let's say
the first step which says now you evaluate the expression on the right hand side fast and then put
it or bind it to the second you know left hand side variable in the left hand side so what happens
even though let's say your first step does not change the state of machine the second state
will certainly change the state of machine right because now you are pointing to some register
you know or you know some memory location and you are saying that now I want to assign whatever
value I have calculated from this expression into that memory location so the moment you do this
you certainly change the state of machine okay so I mean at least I mean we are in a position where
the state of machine may be changed now if you assign the same value let's say to the variable
that you have declared may be earlier in the program you are certainly not changing the state of
machine but then this is the no pop no segment of statement which has the potential to change the
state of machine okay so whenever you see an assignment statement like this think in mind this
two-step you know process two-step now personal semantic another thing that I want to highlight here
is that assignment statements are destructive in the nature so what does it remain I mean see on
the left hand side you have a variable right and this variable might have been initialized in your
program no earlier on I mean this may not be the first time this variable is being used let's say
so in that case what happens as soon as you assign the value of the expression on the right hand
side to this variable the old value of the variable is lost for no ever you cannot recover that
no variable value this should be very no causes if you are writing in your programmer statement
an assignment statement then the effect of that assignment statement will be that now your
previous value of the variable will be lost forever so if you want to use that value in future
better story you know in some other variable that can be helpful later on okay this is very you
know important and we will see you know going ahead this has no certain effect when you try to
reason about the correctness of let's say your program so now let me write down a very simple
maybe function which can not do a simple operation on some numbers so maybe the simplest
my example that is coming in my mind is you know swapping to numbers I mean I hope many of you
might have seen this program if I give you two variables let's say and I want to know swap the
value of the two variable so I'm asking you to write down a function which can do this
and it turns out that this no simple function can be written by just using you know this assignment
expression so maybe you know this is the simplest you know kind of function which we can write
using assignment statement so let me help you with you know initial definition and then we will
reason about this function so so this is a very simple function like you know what we are trying
to write down is you know definition of a function which let's say call swap okay so we are trying
to write down a swap function okay so and let me say that we will use a temporary variable to swap
the two number that is given as an argument so what are the argument to this function we have x and
y okay so these x and y are two numbers which we want to swap no eventually so the definition
of the function maybe something like this so since I want to swap the value of no x and y what I
do as a first step is I maybe you know define a temporary variable temp and then store the value of
x so you have given me the value of x and y as input to this function so what I do is I first let's say
somehow no reserve this value of x because you know this value of x will be destroyed as soon as I
you know write value of y into x okay so I want to maybe you know keep it safe no before I destroy
the old value of x so this is no the intention of writing this you know temporary variable so when
we say temp is equal to x what we have done just now is that you know we saved the old value of
x and maybe the next step that I know 1 to 2 is I want to maybe assign the value of y into x
okay so the moment I did it so see when we are writing program we have intense in behind each line
right so no this is something which is missing in today's software development because you are
asking with the natural language prompt and you are getting the whole code at once right so you never
reason about the partial or the initial segment of a program on your own so but I mean it's always a good
practice when even if you let's say get your whole code from lm you start reasoning about the code
whether the code is meeting the intention of what you wanted okay and that you can do only if you
go through the code not a little bit slowly and carefully and when you go through a code
carefully you always you know look at some initial segment and write and your initial segment keeps
increasing inside until you finish the no reviewing the whole code okay but for every initial segment
also there is some purpose right by that by this time I am doing this particular job for example in
this case when I say temp is equal to x I have some intention right I want to store the previous
value of x maybe before destroying it that's why I am you know creating this not temp is equal to
x so when you go through it slowly you can you know visualize the intention behind all this
statement and then maybe you are in a better position to comprehend the program no properly and
hence you can believe it okay so the temp is equal to x stores the previous value of x before we
destroy it in the next step what we have is x is equal to y right so what is the effect of this
now your value of y has been kept into x and remember does this step you know changes the value of y
so this statement should not change the value of y right because you know x is on the left hand side
so the if you're thinking again in terms of abstract machine if no x and y are the only let's
say memory places that you have no initialize or in this case no x y and temp or three memory
location that you have does till now so certainly the no this line where I'm trying to assign
to x the value of y now only changes the state of you know abstract machine at that location x
it does not change anything on so nothing about y is changed so this is what we want to say
so so at this moment what you have is already no x has the value of y that you gave to this
program and then what you know what what should be the final statement of this program to achieve
the task that you did you wanted okay so I want into y no sound value right whatever was given
as the initial value in x this is what I want in y and you see now why this temp variable you know
comes handy because in the temporary variable you have written the original value of x that you
you know wanted to transfer to y but if you did not store it in temp and you directly let's say
did the no this statement no many people you know might do this mistake or programming for the very
first time they may forget no this line of code and then what they can they would do is no x is
equal to y and y is equal to no x and then no the whole thing no get strong so so what we do here
is we try to you think through this program a little slowly and you will see that this no will
make perfect sense to you and what you want to return is you know the value the current value in x
and y okay so at this no moment in time when you are in executing this code your current value of
x and y must have been swap so this is what we believe so let me you know quickly run this piece
of code and then maybe run some examples of what example let's talk about some simple
input so if what if I pass to this function swap let's say 2 comma 3 okay if I want to
pass 2 comma 3 what do I return what do I you know expect in return 3 comma 2 right so this this
is no nicely you know swapping the value so there is no issue right so let us try to swap things
maybe which are of different types so this is very simple right we had to integer but what let's say
if I have you know first thing as a you know integer and the second thing as a string
see so no whether it's no integer or other kind of not a type that you are passing you know is
in material this function is doing its job perfectly right this is what we intended we want to swap
no value of the variable in these two different value that we have given to this function swap
okay so this looks like a you know correct implementation and by working with these a small
example we can get confidence why this should be correct but again as I said I mean looking at
the program initial segments slowly and no increasing your initial segment gives you more confidence
why this program should work because your program may work I mean if you only rely on testing it
on some you know input it may work for your you know test input but it may not work for some other
tests inputs so no only because it has worked for your input does not guarantee that it will work
for all the input but if you work with the code a little slowly maybe it gives you much more
confidence about the you know behavior of the program so now we will again you know let's talk
about the same you know program and try to write down whatever we discuss no till now as a
specification of the program so when we say specification now whatever we were thinking through
when we were analyzing this program can we also write down our thoughts as something inside
programming language okay so Python and other programming language is also you know provide to
this feature of assertions where you can assert something that you believe it to be true at that
particular moment of time in program okay so this assertions are very useful and I would highly
encourage you know you to write these assertions you know as often as possible so that you know it
it you you get a second you know chance to think about the program or initial segment of the
program and write the meaningful you know intention that you have in mind when you're reading this
program okay and if everything goes you know correct then you have more confidence in the program
for example for this simple program let me know maybe a copy paste the code of the previous thing here
okay so let me copy it and then we paste it here okay so let's call it you know instead of
software rename this function to something different let's say software one okay and now what we
want to do is you remember I mean I had some intention of this statement right so I so after
this is no statement if you if I write let's say assert so assert always you know tries to
assert something you know you are trying to declare something at this particular moment of time
declarations are of the type true or false right your declaration may be no wrong or it may be
right so anything that you know expect after this assert must you know return you boolean values okay
and we know how to you know get boolean values right we have boolean operator or logical operator
to compare no values or variables and then you know tell us whether this true or not so for
example in this simple case after this line of code I certainly want this to be true do you see
what I want is I want them them value is equal to is equal to the value of x okay so let's say
uh so so assert statement I know this kind of semantic so you assert something and if let's say
this something that you have asserted is not correct you may also optionally print something which
can you know help you that you know this statement was not correct okay so let's say if this
statement is not correct no I just want to know maybe say uh failed at know the very first let's
say step let's have failed at what I mean just you know this this is for my hint that which of
the assertions you know I have failed I may want to write multiple assertions in my program then
but when it fails I want to know which one has failed okay so let's say you know if I see the
this being printed out I can you know make make out that you know this is the assertion that I failed
so at this particular moment of time I certainly want these two values to be true right so I can
expect this to pass when I uh run this program okay so can we run the program and see whether this
is you know passing for so let me know first compile this program and if we run this program again
maybe you know copy the same thing okay and now instead of swap time let's say call this new
function swap temp on and if I run it it passes right so there is no no error right so so no this
statement is certainly you know changing the value of only temporary valuable and the value in
the temporary very well after this no statement has been executed is the value of x okay so this is
no perfectly fine so there is no no error that you know we get when we run this so
what about another maybe statement that I want so what was the effect of this no can I write
down something no similar let's say assert can I write down that at this moment of time
so whatever you know was true previously is there and after executing you know this particular
statement x is equal to y I also want something no new to be true so no I wanted no temp to be x but I
maybe also want to so what the law effect of the last statement that x is equal to y right
in x you have put the value of i so certainly no I want at this particular time x is equal to
equal to y no since I have executed this statement just now I may want this to be true and let's say
you know call it if this does not turned out to be no correct then I want to maybe you know print
this statement okay so so now let me recompile this thing this part of the code
so you see I mean what I'm saying is you know I want to you know here claim that since I have not
done this you know part I want you know this new thing to be added to my previous you know
knowledge or whatever I have stood till the last point okay so I have done maybe no this extra
step in the last assignment so this equality should be true now in addition to the previous one
so do you see I mean this should no return us true or false I mean we have run the code already
and if we let's say now run it on 2.3 what do we get so so it's complaining right so it's saying
that you have you know failed that too so something went wrong here right certainly I mean this
expression is you know no more correct so what might have gone wrong so can this statement go
wrong at this particular point in time so the semantics or the meaning of you know this assignment
expression is that whatever was you know the value in why you just keep it in next so just
after executing this to certainly we don't want to say that this statement cannot be true right
because this is what we did right now and we are not doing anything else now after this step so
this must be true so what went wrong then I mean is it true now
see so as we discuss I mean the assignments are destructive right so as soon as you assign
into x the value of y right so you have changed the value of x right so if initially temp was
no is equal to is equal to x now temp may not be equal to equal to x right because no temp
has not been changed but x has been changed you see the no advantage of writing you know these
assertions so at this particular moment in time I I know that my you know value of x has been
destroyed but my value of temp has not been no change and now if initially this was true
it may not be true now right because my last statement has not changed another value of temp
but it has changed change the value of x so this is the reason why you know this line of
code is maybe failing okay so this assertion is failing so no instead of let's say so let me
know copy let me keep it so that you can refer to it later on so let me write it down again
and maybe commit this line of code we don't want know this whole thing now what we are saying is
we can only claim this safely maybe after this you know instructions on this point in time
okay and then if we run so what do you expect now select me now correct so let's run it and then
if we run it again now there is no problem right so now with this one we can see that this is
perfectly no correct okay so it's not failing at this no position so similarly what to write down
no so since we have you know taken we took some lessons from the last two assignment statement
we should be a little careful when we try to write down the effect of let's say the last
statement which is y is equal to temp so what can we write down here the effect of the last
statement can we write down so assert now since I'm changing y to the value of temp so is it okay to
write down no this one so let's check it let's say if not then I want to maybe print the string failed
at 3 okay and let me run it this should be correct right because again in the last statement
that we have executed is y is equal to temp and after that no we are immediately claiming this
thing so this must be tried this particular moment in time so let me run it and if we run it I
don't see there isn't any error right okay so this is certainly no we want to
we can you know confidently write down you know for this particular program but see I mean
these assertions although tell us true things about the you know initial segment of program they
don't say something very useful that maybe we want to write down and check for this overall program
right so at the last you know at this moment in time when you're exiting before existing you
are asserting something which is not very informative right what you're saying is no y is equal
to is equal to temp and temp is something that you have created no inside this no function okay
and if you don't know the code that's happening inside the function just by looking at you know
this assertion it may not make a must sense of what this no function is doing so we we want to know
some stronger or you know more meaningful or helpful assertions which can help us relate
the implementation with the intention of the code so so the intention of the code was that I
mean this no original value of x and y should have been swap okay so to achieve that what we do
is we define some ghost variable okay so no no I'm going to introduce you to the concept of ghost
variable and these are actually like you know other variable but the intention of ghost variable
is completely different okay so these are purely for verification purpose and to you know ensure
that the code is behaving the way you want after you know let's say you're you know confirm that
the program works as it is this ghost variable can safely be removed from no code without affecting
the effect of the code okay so the the whole sole purpose of this ghost variable are to ensure that
the code behaves no properly and you should be able to write down know what you want to write for
this particular piece of code okay so let me again I'll give you you know maybe I can copy and
paste the same code from here see and then paste the code and what we want to do is now let's say
not collect swap temp but what I want to call it is swap temp maybe you know very quiet okay
this is what we want to say now we want to know say something meaningful about this program will
which should relate to the intention okay so the intention that we wanted to say is the final
value of you know x that is written from this no code is the original value of y right and
the final value of y that is written by this no piece of code is the original value of x so this
is what we want to maybe say in this for this no piece of code so what we can say is we can
initialize to ghost variable which are nothing but just to capture the original value of x and y
so what we can say we can use something like this let's say no use a meaningful name like no
x original it to store the original value of you know x and y original to store the original value
of you know y and let's say the very first step in my program is I just stored the original
value of so the whole sole purpose of this you know is to define kind of a you know
you want before the you know value of x and y gets destroyed you maybe want to store it in some
variable and name it properly so that you can refer to it later on in your program okay so
x original and y originals only you know intention is to capture the no original state
no for reasoning okay so so let me write it down only intention of writing now this
piece of code is to share
original state for reasoning
okay now we have since we have captured now our first statement is you know
okay so this is the only purpose of this statement is to capture no this thing and then let me
know remove all of this maybe you know we don't need here or I mean let's let's remove this
a no intermediate assertions for the time being we'll put some new assertions which can be
you know meaningful in the current context maybe also this one no assume that no for with this
no initial original state no being captured in x original and y original if you can make assertion
something no like this let's say at this step that you know finally when no before you
exit your x should be nothing but no y original okay and y
then we will be happy right so this is what was our original intention otherwise we will say
that shop has failed so we see so we started the program so so imagine that now this piece of
code which I have highlighted from here to at this point can be either you know let's say
developed by you or LLM or by some you know third you know party and they have given you this
function okay so what we can do is we can annotate this function properly to write down whatever
was our original intention of us in code for this function okay so original intention was that
if let's say x original and y original represent the initial state of you know x and y whatever
was the value in x and y then finally after executing whatever code you give I want something like
this to be true right that we I want to know safely assert that you know x should be equal to
at this moment in time when you are exiting the program just before exiting x the value in x
should be same as the original value of y so that's why you know this goes variable so remember
if you don't define this goes variable there is no other way you know which can help you assert
something like this here right because you want to relate the because this is a special you know
case where we want to relate our final state of you know this x y with the original state of you know
x y right so if you don't distort the original state since this assignment statements are you know
destructive in nature you cannot assert something like this at the okay so the best or the most
convenient way is you store both the original state in you know this goes variable and then later on
if we do this you know in the very beginning later on towards before exiting the program we are
in a position to assert something like this okay so do you see I mean this is exactly what we want
from the program so if we can write down this we are sure and if you can you know get confirmed that
no this is right then we are sure that the program is doing know what we intended it to do okay
so certainly I mean you know this is something we would like to know whether the program is doing
or not so let me now or call this function on some you know input to just check some
maybe you know pass it an extreme x and then maybe two okay so if I want to let's swap these
two things you know first one is string x instead of not giving some value I just give a string
okay so we did not run this you know piece of port just above this so if the block of port does not
recognize it but let's say if we run it then we now run the we call this function
so what we got is these values you know swap right so certainly I mean so this is good okay so
but then how to so one advantage of let's say you know writing this kind of you know meaningful and
correct specification is that if let's just by some you know chance your LLM or whatever the third
part is is not giving you the correct code it's giving you let's say some you know
minutely let's say incorrect code you know there is some mistake which is very minute so can
you know this kind of or I mean are these assertions good enough to cast those kind of bug okay so
if you are sure about that no by capturing the initial state if I want this to be true for the
final step then I can actually you know figure out some very subtle bug inside the code also
let's say this code is not you know this seal but a you know big piece of code which you cannot
know go and you know investigate line by line then then also I mean this kind of you know assertions
can help you get rid of or at least detect those kind of you know bug so so no the third attempt
what I want to do is maybe I want to do some you know bug in this implementation and then show you
that this you know assertion can help you figure out that kind of bug for example let me copy paste
first this code here okay and now so let's do a very maybe not trivial mistake maybe just just
comment this okay see I mean this is a part of code that we want to modify or no introduce bug
because you know this is what came from LLM or third party and so the very first line and third
line was written by us understanding our intention okay so so if let's say we forget to you know
comment this kind of we we we we comment this no one line of code and then you try to run this
and maybe you know again call on some the same value maybe same thing if you want to
you see I mean where did so this assertion at the last is not true right so since no we
have commented this piece of code now you know that the value of x has not been changed right although
you have changed the value of no y to x the value of x has not been changed and that's causes
this no error right that your x does not have the no original value of y okay but your y may have
the original value of x so so this assertion fails why this fails because there are two things which
has to be true for this assertion to be you know true the first one and the second one okay and one
of them does not hold true that's why this assertion fails and you know immediately that there is some
you know error in the code so what you know just know to summarize what I wanted to say is if you
invest a little bit of time trying to understand the intention of writing any function you know
and that intention if you can translate from natural language to this assertions then the chances
of no you know figuring out whether there is a bug in the no code that has been produced either by
LLM or any third party agent increases and if those assertions pass then you are more confident
that no your program will not have any error now what I'm saying is if those assertions pass
then you have more confident only you know you know in a partial sense I mean if the assertions pass
you cannot be confirmed that the code is correct because no assertions you are testing only
on some input right we are testing on only this kind of input but then you know some there may be
some other input where you know these assertions may fail right if the assertion passes on all
possible input let's say for some know and if you can do this and check in some way then you
can be certainly sure right that the code is correct but since we cannot check this assertion
being you know true always for all possible input we cannot certainly even you know say after
you know checking on finite number of input whether the code is correct or not so you don't
have 100 percent guarantee but certainly you have more guarantee because you know multiple
input you have checked the behavior to be true what you wanted it to be okay so these assertions
are certainly better than you know one or two you know test cases but to make it you know worth
while you need to somehow generate a lot of you know inputs you know for this program and then
check whether you know you know these assertions are failing or not okay so let me uh
so so one advantage another advantage that I wanted to tell you here is that see
you know these assertions somehow capture the intent of your you know programming so what you need
to give I mean you just need to give the inputs right and run this program on multiple input
so in test cases you know you know if I have to contrast the situation with you know checking your
program on multiple you know input output pair what you also need to give is you know the what
is the correct output that you are expecting at each of those input right so test cases are normally
those input output pair not only input right but here in this case if we write down or invest time
in writing correct assertions are different you know programming uh stages then what you are do
you have to do is just you know give me enough uh number of you know valid inputs on which I can
run this program okay and you don't need to tell me exactly what is the value of output that I you
know want to expect at this particular input because now those things are internally captured by
these assertions so you just need to generate a lot of you know inputs to the program and not the
no output value once you have no written these assertions carefully so that's also you know
another kind of good advantage of writing the assertions you know properly okay so let's no go ahead
with this uh I think now you know let me you know uncomment this thing all let me keep it there and
comment this section of course so that you can review it okay so now we have written correct
specification for sure right correct and if we are writing the correct code so so
we should not only you know write correct specification uh you know final specification and
correct code but you can also insert some intermediate no assertions that we were actually uh
you know inserting previously as you say you know as you have seen in the very first example we have
I have annotated the program with multiple assertions so let's do a final you know round of
insertion of all those okay so let me write on first the whole thing code so certainly
there this is what I want to be you know true at the in if this is true at the beginning so I'm
very much you know sure about that but then what is it not like a complete proof of no correctness
of this program so if I want to fix since you know this is not the only thing that I might might
be seeing when I get the code I may also want to you know introduce some intermediate annotations
or assertions that you know can be helpful in figuring now catching some other kind of box okay so
so let me write it down so maybe after this line of code so what what do you expect I mean what
shall be uh correct when I so let me uncomment this code because now I we want to run this piece of
so after you know temp is equal to x what what can we assert safely so can we assert that you know
temp's value is equal to is equal to let's say no x original okay but temp's value temp's value is
also x but then no we we want to not talk about the values of this you know in temporary
variable in terms of the original value because that's what is our intention right that temp
no retains the original value of x so writing temp is equal to equal to x is also no perfectly valid
but why we are writing here temp is equal to x original because maybe we want to carry a you know
forward this information no towards the next step okay and we don't want it to change okay so
you'll see in the next step know when we say and you you can actually differentiate between
writing down temp is equal to equal to x and x temp is equal to equal to x original in the next step
so let's for the timing write temp is equal to no x original and if it's not true again I mean you can
say you know failed let's say the very first place so when we have you know this x is equal to
is equal to y what can we say please can we still let me you know ask can we still write down temp
is equal to is equal to original here do you think this is correct
this should be correct right because you have not changed so to your last statement that
you have seen just now has changed the state of x okay and what are the
you know left hand and right hand side of this no equality uh relation this is temp and x
so x original has not been changed right you have only changed the x so you know that's why we
have written probably here you know x original that we wanted you know this uh you know it's part
of statement to be true here as well okay so this part of a statement is true here also only
because we are writing x original and not x okay so now we can safely write down here you know
that temp is equal to is equal to x original because the our last statement is neither changing
nor changing x original so this statement should be true and maybe no at this particular moment of
time I can claim something more right so what what I can claim here is that my x now becomes
no y original okay again you see I instead of writing x is equal to is equal to y what I have
written is my x is equal to y original because till this point y's value has not been changed so y
and y original is same essentially we can write both and both will be correct but this will be
helpful when we try to prove the final property of the program okay so at this moment of time what
we can safely claim is our temporary variable has x original and the current value in x is the
original value that came into y okay so let me write down again I want to default let's say
I want to maybe no print fill that too here because in case if I you know this thing is not true
you know right now I'm guessing that this should be true but if it is not true it should you know
return this print message and I should be able to see this now what about the you know very
last one so what can we write here so shall we so what can we write so when we have done let's say
this last step where y is equal to 10 okay so what can we safely know I said this particular
point in time so where did we get this so this is our final thing right so this is certainly
another final thing that we want to say but can we write down some you know detailed
you know explanation of the last statement also so can we write down that since we have done
y is equal to 10 maybe you know we want to say immediately here that y should y's value should
be you know equal to temporary okay and what we also want to see here is the temp is equal to is
equal to x original and maybe what else I want to see okay so so y is equal to temp for sure okay
temp value is equal to x original not about no this last thing do we think that this is still true
because y original has not changed and you know x has also been not touched by the you know
code I'm sorry
so we were writing down this piece of wooden we by mistake inserted this whole thing okay so what
we are saying is we want to you know maybe copy and paste this thing right we want this to be
not true at this particular moment of time and if it is not true let's say we want to say
fail at three you see we are incrementally building the number of you know
proposition that we want to be true right initially we are saying that no we want this to be true
we want it to be retained even after the second one but then we want some additional thing to be
true right by the second statement and what we are saying here is now we want you know this new
thing to be true here but no we can safely assume that all the previous things are also true
because my last statement does not change these are touches those variables so I can safely
actually write down these things okay and that's how now if you know all these things are true
then you can you know make sense that why you know this should imply this one right no you can
easily see right that y you know x should be equal to y original right because see this is exactly
what we have written here right that x is equal to y original and your y is equal to
x original so y is equal to x original because y is already is equal to 10 and 10 is equal to
x original so y is equal to x original so this is like a complete proof why this is programs should
work okay so if you write no assertions like this a detailed set of assertions like this we
can almost be sure that no will catch any bug that will come in the code if we run it you know
enough number of time with different numbers of different no input buried input okay so we can
we need a run again the same thing for just once or maybe you know this same piece of code we want
to run it again so it's failing because no we have not defined this thing okay we have not
know around this piece of what once we run this piece of what and then if we run we get the
sort value okay so it was just you know highlight so today's no lecture we just wanted to highlight
that there are ways to validate code that you write okay it's not that you cannot validate
and by writing these assertions my intention was to tell you very you know clearly the
semantics of this assignment statement so semantic assignment statement is you only you are
changing that variable and nothing else so you know if you have some way to store the previous
value of the variables then you can assert or you can claim meaningful property about your program
very easily okay so that's was the not only purpose of this lecture so please go through the
lecture today that we we discussed on the concept today these are very important assignment is
you know one of the most important statement in any programming language especially if it is
imperative programming language and we should clearly understand the semantics okay and in
case of need where you know you can not trust let's say the piece of what that you have generated
you should do this you know line by line analysis and you should write down your intentions
using this assert statement so assert statement so it's very useful okay anything that comes inside
this assert statement no it is a you know no Boolean expression and it always you know you
values to idle to or false so if you generate you know enough number of let's say input to the
program that you are trying to verify then there is high chance that you will you know catch any
you know error box that may be present in your program okay so with this no I would like to
in this lecture so what I have given here as an R2 you know assignment problems for you to think
about so this did know this was you know one of the way to swap to number which is very safe
where you use use a temporary variable but many people you know try to you know trick and then
try to come up with it's a program is does not use any let's say additional variable like
there we use an additional variable which we call temp now if someone asks you can you do this
without using any additional variable so there are multiple ways to you know do that but then
there can be error right in those ways so you should always know check whether those tricky ways of
swapping to numbers are correct or not and for that I have given you you know two sample programs
you just work through this program and try to repeat you know the kind of annotation or assertion
that we have done for the safe you know this temporary variable swap program for these two
setup program also so please take your time go through these you know the examples you know
slowly the way we did today's example and try to see whether you can write down safely those
assertions and get it right or not okay okay so with this I will conclude today's lecture and
we'll meet in the next lecture see you then